<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references.
-->
<!ENTITY RFC3697 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3697.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that
most I-Ds might want to use. (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-ietf-jjmb-ietf-ipv6-only-incremental-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902,
noDerivativesTrust200902,
        or pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only
	 necessary if the full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="IETF IPv6-only Wi-Fi Incremental">
      Incremental deployment of IPv6-only Wi-Fi for IETF Meetings
    </title>

    <author fullname="John Jason Brzozowski" initials="J."
            surname="Brzozowski">
      <organization>Comcast Cable</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1701 John F. Kennedy Blvd.</street>
          <city>Philadelphia</city>
          <region>PA</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>john_brzozowski@cable.comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David Schinazi" initials="D." surname="Schinazi">
      <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>95014</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>dschinazi@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='S.' surname='Cheshire' fullname='Stuart Cheshire'>
      <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>95014</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>cheshire@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lorenzo Colitti" initials="L." surname="Colitti">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>lorenzo@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Erik Kline" initials="E." surname="Kline">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>ek@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jen Linkova" initials="J." surname="Linkova">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>furry@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Marcus Keane" initials="M." surname="Keane">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>marcus.keane@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paul Saab" initials="P." surname="Saab">
      <organization>Facebook</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>ps@fb.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="26" month="June" year="2017" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Ops Area</area>

    <workgroup>v6ops</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The purpose of this document is to provide a blueprint and guidance
      for deploying IPv6-only Wi-Fi at IETF meetings. This document outlines
      infrastructure and operational guidance that operators must consider
      when deploying IPv6-only networks using NAT64 and DNS64 to support
      communication to legacy IPv4-only services.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <?rfc needLines="10" ?>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The purpose of this document is to provide a blueprint and guidance
      for deploying IPv6-only Wi-Fi at IETF meetings. This document outlines
      infrastructure and operational guidance that operators must consider
      when deploying IPv6-only networks using NAT64 and DNS64 to support
      communication to legacy IPv4-only services.</t>

      <t>One of the main strengths of the IETF has always been an insistence
      on running code. As such IETF meetings were one of the first
      deployments of a dual-stack network to help test the first
      implementations of IPv6. Many years later, as several networks are
      shifting towards IPv6-only, it is the reponsibility of the IETF to
      lead the trend and make their main network IPv6-only.</t>

      <t>This document outlines the requirements and design principles for an IPv6-only
      network infrastructure that includes support for IPv4-only content.
      It also discusses techniques and requirements for network
      management, telemetry, and the operations and support for the IPv6-only
      network. Recommendations and best practices for operations and support
      will be provided, however, alternate approaches may be utilized.
      Disabling or removal of IPv4 stacks is out of scope for this document.
      This document focuses on the explicit provisioning of IPv6-only using
      NAT64 <xref target="RFC6146">RFC6146</xref> and DNS64 <xref
      target="RFC6147">RFC6147</xref> to access IPv4-only content and services.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Design Principles">
      <section title="Network Infrastructure">
        <t>The following a specific network design details that are minimally
        required to support an IPv6-only network that utilized NAT64 and
        DNS64. The following have been drawn from real deployment scenarios
        for large scale uses of IPv6-only with NAT64 and DNS64. The parameters
        specified here are specific to providing IPv6-only connectivity. It is
        assumed that IPv6-only is provisioned and that IPv4 stacks remain
        active on network and host interfaces. The disabling or removal of
        IPv4 stacks from hosts or routers is out of scope for this document.
        As such it is important to note that link local IPv4 <xref
        target="RFC3927">RFC3927</xref> will likely remain active and will
        appear on hosts and network infrastructure.</t>

        <t>The following section outlines the requirement to provisioning
        IPv6-only. We minimally assume that SLAAC will be utilized, however, for
        completeness the parameters required for DHCPv6 <xref
        target="RFC3315">RFC3315</xref> and <xref
        target="RFC3736">RFC3736</xref> are also provided:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>IPv6-only - hosts are expected to be provisioned with IPv6-only
            connectivity, however, link local IPv4 is likely to be
            present.</t>

            <t>RA interval is minimally recommended to be set to 4
            seconds.</t>

            <t>At least one prefix information option (PIO) must be included
            in router advertisements, the transmitted PIO must correspond to
            the IPv6 prefix that is valid for a given IPv6 link.</t>

            <t>The use of SLAAC <xref target="RFC4862">RFC4862</xref> must be
            signalled by the network, specifically for each transmitted PIO
            the A but must be set to 1 (one).</t>

            <t>DHCPv6 support should be included but is not required, as such
            both the M and O bits must be set to 1 (one). Whether stateless or
            stateful DHCPv6 is used both the DNS Server IPv6 address and DNS
            Search List options <xref target="RFC6106">RFC6106</xref> must
            minimally be included. The DNS server IPv6 address(es) must be
            those used for DNS64. It is recommended that these values be
            identical to those used in the IPv6 router advertisements that
            include the RDNSS <xref target="RFC6106">RFC6106</xref> options.
            If DHCPv6 support is deployed stateless DHCPv6 must minimally be
            available.</t>

            <t>IPv6 router advertisements must include the RDNSS options. Both
            the DNS Server IPv6 address(es) and DNS-SL are required. If DHCPv6
            support is deployed the values sent here for RDNSS are recommended
            to match those sent via DHCPv6.</t>
          </list>
        To ensure seamless and to support an incremental deployment
        of IPv6-only access to legacy dual stack infrastructure should remain
        available. The following are recommended approaches that may be
        considered to achieve the same.</t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>The deployment of IPv6-only with NAT64 and DNS64 may very well
            help to identify applications, services, or use cases that are not
            entirely compatible with the same. It is therefore important to
            ensure that users of IP networks, whether wired or wireless, have
            access to legacy dual stack infrastructure as a fallback. For
            wireless network it is recommend to have a secondary SSID labelled
            accordingly, e.g. example-ssid-dual-stack or example-ssid-legacy.
            For wired network connectivity having secondary ports that are
            dual stack enabled is also recommended.</t>
          </list>
        This document assumes that dual stack connectivity is
        available by default and that IPv4-only connectivity is no longer
        supported. As such it is out of scope for this document outline
        fallback or access to legacy connectivity that is IPv4-only.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Services">
      <t>The following network services are required for an IPv6-only where
      support for and access to IPv4 content, services, and applications are
      required.</t>

      <section title="DNS64">
        <t>The following recommendations apply to the use and deployment of
        DNS64:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Use of the well known DNS64 prefix per <xref
            target="RFC6052">RFC6052</xref></t>

            <t>It is also recommended that query logging be enabled for DNS64,
            performance impacts of query logging must be noted but are largely
            out of scope for this document. Query logging is essential to
            determine the volume and make up of DNS queries and replies that
            are are specific to DNS64 and IPv4-only content, services, and
            applications.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT64">
        <t>The following recommendations apply to the use and deployment of
        NAT64:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>DNS64 is a critical aspect to direct requests from IPv6-only
            hosts to a NAT64 service.</t>

            <t>NAT64 configurations vary widely, port allocation techniques
            are largely out of scope for this document. One-to-one (1:1)
            mappings can be used to allocate an IPv4 address per connected
            device or alternatively blocks of IPv4 ports can also be assigned
            per device, each has different properties. It is generally
            recommended to allocate IPv4 ports per device in an effort to
            maximize IPv4 utilization for NAT64.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="DHCPv6">
        <t>Support for DHCPv6 may be required in some deployments. If
        required, parameters pertaining to IPv6 router discovery may
        requirement adjustment. The following outlines the guidance specific
        to the use of DHCPv6:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Stateless DHCPv6 SHOULD be supported to facilitate the
            transmission of DNS servers IPv6 address(es) and DNS search
            lists.</t>

            <t>Stateful DHCPv6 for address assignment MAY be supported, but is
            not required. If stateful DHCPv6 is used the DNS parameters
            mentioned above must be included.</t>

            <t>While stateful DHCPv6 is not strictly required for host
            addressing, if support for IPv6 prefix delegation becomes
            necessary stateful DHCPv6 will likely be mandatory. (see Future
            Work) The details of IPv6 prefix delegation is out of scope for
            this document.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="User Equipment">
      <t>Host Address Assignment and Configuration:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Hosts MUST support SLAAC.</t>

          <t>Hosts SHOULD support RDNSS <xref target="RFC6106">RFC6106</xref>
          for the acquisition of DNS
          server IPv6 addresses and a DNS Search List.</t>

          <t>Hosts MAY support DHCPv6 for address acquisition, the use of
          DHCPv6 for address acquisition is not prohibited.</t>

          <t>DHCPv6 option to configure DNS server option 23 and domain search
          list option 24 <xref target="RFC3646">RFC3646</xref>
          address MUST be implemented if DHCPv6 is to be utilized.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>IPv4 support:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>The IPv4 stacks of hosts MAY remain enabled, which means that
            Link Local IPv4 <xref target="RFC3927">RFC3927</xref>
            (168.254/16) addresses MAY continue to be
            present and in use. Disabling of the IPv4 stack of hosts is out of
            scope for this document.</t>

            <t>Hosts MUST support connecting to IPv4-only servers by using the
            NAT64/DNS64. Possible solutions include 464XLAT <xref target="RFC6877">RFC6877</xref>,
            "Bump-in-the-Host" <xref target="RFC6535">RFC6535</xref> and Happy Eyeballs v2
            <xref target="HEv2"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Management">
      <t>The focus of this document is user equipment and hosts. The network
      and network service requirements are oriented around providing IPv6-only
      connectivity to use to allow for the use of NAT64 and DNS64 to maintain
      reachability to IPv4-only content, applications, and services.
      Operations and management of the underlying network is technically out
      of scope for this document, however, given the relevance of the same to
      the focus of this draft some guidance is being provided.</t>

      <t>Strictly speaking the primary requirement for the underlying network
      is that IPv6 is supported along with the services required to enable the
      use of NAT64 and DNS64. This suggests that the underlying network could
      in fact be dual stack for management and operations. It is required that
      the provisioning of IPv4 for user equipment and host connectivity not be
      supported. User equipment or host facing interfaces must not have
      following:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Non-link local IPv4 addresses</t>
          <t>DHCPv4 is not supported or enabled</t>
          <t>DNS services over IPv4 is not supported or enabled</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Given the above, within a given VLAN it is possible and likely that
      IPv4 may be observed, present, and possibly used. It is out of scope for
      this document to prevent the use of IPv4 entirely.</t>

      <t>Depending on the level of readiness IPv6-only network management may
      or may not be possible. Network management and operations includes but
      is not limited to the following:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Remote access to network infrastructure via SSH or telnet</t>
          <t>Remote SNMP communications</t>
          <t>Remote NETCONF communications</t>
          <t>Remote Syslog communications</t>
        </list>
      While it is strongly recommended that all network management
      and operations be performed over IPv6-only it is not strictly required.
      However, it is important to note that the presence and use of IPv4 for
      network management and operations must not impede or impact the use of
      IPv6-only with NAT64 and DNS64.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Telemetry and Monitoring">
      <t>At this point in time, IPv6-only networks with no IPv4 support at all
      are still not widespread and may expose issues in host operating systems
      or applications. It is therefore recommended to establish telemetry of
      how hosts are getting addresses provisioned and accessing the Internet.
      In order to preserve the privacy of users of the network, it is
      paramount that connectivity information (e.g. DNS64 records) cannot be
      correlated with individual client nodes.</t>

      <t>We can measure how hosts:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Configure IPv6 addresses (SLAAC, DHCPv6) and which ones they use</t>
          <t>Configure DNS server addresses (RDNSS vs DHCPv6)</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>We can measure what percentage of the traffic:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Uses native IPv6</t>
          <t>Uses NAT64</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Recording the most common hostnames that require the DNS64 to
      synthesize would also allow to establish a list of the most prominent
      IPv4-only services.</t>

      <t>Observing the TCP/UDP ports used by applications that still leverage
      IPv4 link-local on an IPv6-only network will also help prepare for the
      time when routers stop switching IPv4 traffic altogether.</t>

      <t>Given that some users may have devices running legacy IPv4-only
      software, the network should provide a different fallback network that
      is dual-stack. It is worth measuring the number of users that switch to
      this network, and possibly use an anonymous survey asking users what
      software failure caused them to switch.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Support for User Applications and Services ">
      <t>Following is a list of commonly used applications and services that
      are expected to operate, without incident, when used in an IPv6-only
      environment that utilizes NAT64 and DNS64. The list below is not
      exhaustive.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>VPN</t>
          <t>Chat</t>
          <t>Email</t>
          <t>SSH/Telnet</t>
          <t>Git</t>
          <t>Voice</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Recording the most common hostnames that require the DNS64 to
      synthesize would also allow to establish a list of the most prominent
      IPv4-only services.</t>

      <t>Observing the TCP/UDP ports used by applications that still leverage
      IPv4 link-local on an IPv6-only network will also help prepare for the
      time when routers stop switching IPv4 traffic altogether.</t>

      <t>Given that some users may have devices running legacy IPv4-only
      software, the network should provide a different fallback network that
      is dual-stack. It is worth measuring the number of users that switch to
      this network, and possibly use an anonymous survey asking users what
      software failure caused them to switch.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Support and Operations">
      <t>Most every network has customers or end users of some sort, therefore
      it essential to ensure that end users or consumers of the have means to
      do the following while transitions are occurring in networks and related
      infrastructure. One key item referenced earlier is the availability of
      temporary fallback networks that support legacy communications.</t>

      <t>The following outline additional items that end users must have
      available to communicate with network operators. All of the items below
      must be available via dual stack connectivity.</t>

      <section title="Reporting Issues (Ticketing)">
        <t>Tools and systems that can be used to report issues with
        applications, services, or content must be available for end-users.
        Network and systems operators are responsible for acknowledging and
        classifying issues and ultimately ensuring that the same are properly
        addressed. Specifically to this document &ldquo;fixed&rdquo; is meant
        to imply that proper support for IPv6 is available. In some cases
        network and system operators may need to implement temporary
        workarounds to ensure that end users can access the desired content,
        application, or service.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Interactive support (Slack, email)">
        <t>Interactive support is often desired in lieu or in conjunction with
        traditional support models like trouble ticket creation. It is
        recommended that interactive support be available via real time and
        near real time mechanisms like Slack or electronic mail (e-mail).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Known Client-side Issues">
      <t>Following are known client side issues that are specific to the
      deployment of IPv6-only networks and/or the use of NAT64/DNS64:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Use of literal IPv4 addresses - the use of literal IPv4 addresses
          is a known issue given the approach that is documented in this I-D.
          Addressing the use of literal IPv4 addresses is out of scope for
          this document.</t>

          <t>Unreachable but valid AAAA RR in the DNS - in some cases a valid
          AAAA RR is returns by the DNS, however, if the same is unreachable
          or is not configured the presence of the same will prevent a DNS64
          query which in turn prevents the use of the NAT64 to reach the
          target host references by the address in the AAAA DNS RR.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The vastness of the IPv6 address space often makes it more
          difficult to scan the same unlike legacy IPv4-only or dual stack IP
          networks. It is conceivable that IPv6-only network represent a
          reduction in attack surface area which in turn could be viewed a
          security improvement compared to IPv4-only or dual stack IP
          networks.</t>

          <t>Given the criticality of the DNS64 for reachability to the NAT64,
          poisoning of one or both could represent a vector for the attack of
          the DNS64 and NAT64 which could in turn impact the end user
          experience. Worse poisoning of the DNS64 and/or NAT64 could result
          in redirection of end use devices to malicious hosts. It is likely
          that this vulnerability is no greater in IPv6-only networks
          utilizing DNS64 and NAT64 compared to traditional IPv4-only or dual
          stack networks.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="future" title="Future Work">
      <t>The following items are out of scope for this document, however, the
      following are listed as future work items specific to incremental
      IPv6-only deployments: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Support for IPv6 prefix delegation</t>

          <t>Disabling IPv4 stacks at some point in the future</t>

          <t>Fully deprecating the fallback legacy IPv4 network</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="industry" title="Related Industry Efforts">
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Comcast new building and IPv6-only (John Jason Brzozowski
          &lt;john_brzozowski@comcast.com&gt;)</t>

          <t>Microsoft corporate IT IPv6-only? (Marcus Keane
          &lt;marcus.keane@microsoft.com&gt;)</t>

          <t>Google (Jen Linkova &lt;furry@google.com&gt;)</t>

        </list></t>
    </section>
<!--
    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank the following, in alphabetical order,
      for their contributions:</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>
-->
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3315'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3646'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3736'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4862'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6052'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6106'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6146'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6147'?>

      <reference anchor='HEv2'>
          <front>
              <title>Happy Eyeballs Version 2</title>
              <author fullname="David Schinazi" initials="D." surname="Schinazi">
                  <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
              </author>
              <author fullname="Tommy Pauly" initials="T." surname="Pauly">
                  <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
              </author>
              <date month='June' year='2017' />
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-v6ops-rfc6555bis' />
          <format type='TXT' target='https://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-ietf-v6ops-rfc6555bis.txt' />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3927'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6535'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6877'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
